I wanted to first ask you guys how are
you doing how's everything how are you
and and your families and you know
without anything personal just what's
going on over there in Toronto so I'm
doing well as all the people I love and
care about including Chris and there's
no in-person classes at the University
of Toronto so I've been switching
everything over to virtual the
psychology department the department
physically closed on Friday my phottix
but the entire university will be
physically closed as a month beer
Tuesday I think they're trying to keep
it open as long as possible for
libraries and whatnot but I expect that
that's gonna end
shortly because the premier has asked us
to go into pretty much lockdown so and
the University of course being publicly
funded a university will follow what the
premier says so I fully expect that that
will be it when what's gonna happen I
don't know going forward I've already
received one email indicating that the
courses that I'm supposed to teach in
May and June
nothing official has been said but I
should plan for them to be done totally
virtually as well so that's what's
happening sort of professionally and
personally what's happening virtually is
I've done a couple of talks with Jordan
Hall around kovat 19 and issues around
it around rationality and faith and then
starting Monday I'm going to offer a
live streaming free meditation course
for people so that they will be able to
go come on
and I'll take them through like a 10 to
12 week meditation course when I know
it'll be mornings 9:30 Eastern Standard
Time 9:30 to 10:00 I'll usually teach
probably a new principal Monday and
Thursdays and then in between we'll also
just meet regularly and sit together so
that's something I'm gonna try and do to
help people out and Peter Lindbergh and
I are also putting together he's trying
to revise some sort of a virtual stoah
they've got some of the most famous
Stoics involved current Stoics I mean it
was not like we resurrected anybody and
no Seneca Seneca will be yeah
so we're gonna be offering that for
people as a place where they can go also
to well try to cultivate some in-person
stoicism to give them a way of dealing
with some of the extra strains that this
is putting on their lives so that's
that's sort of where I'm at right now
hmm so how about you Christian is there
anything you want to add to that no not
really I'm also fine my me and mine are
fine so far um we've been very fortunate
I think comparably here next to much of
the rest of the world I think and
because I've been I've been off work for
some months anyway so my day-to-day life
hasn't changed a whole lot although I'm
learning that there's a difference
between like elective solitude and
solitude by ordinance the activities on
the ground aren't all that different
that feeling is a little bit different
it has it's not quite an ordinance yet
here but it's that's just shy of that
it's like we haven't been ordered to
remain cloistered in our homes but but
everything is as John said everything's
more or less shuttered so you really you
don't have a lot of options if you want
to venture out anyway but yeah I would
say so far so good so far so good
yeah how are you doing Andrew Oh
something first I do person I were both
talking just before you came into the
room that we were actually very pleased
with how our both our federal and
provincial governments are handling this
we're very happy about that and we think
they're doing an excellent job mmm
that's good to know
yeah about me personally well it's very
interesting because I'm an overworked
underpaid teacher I would say so in the
past
months I've been working crazily doing a
lot of classes and also doing this kind
of thing so so I've been overworked
basically and a little bit burnt out and
so now I'm on total lockdown I've been
we've been on total lockdown for about a
week here in France and luckily we moved
last year to the edge of Paris so we
have a little garden hmm so I'm feeling
like I'm very lucky compared to a lot of
my friends and colleagues who are stuck
in little apartments in Paris and they
can't leave without a piece of paper
basically you know they they need to
have a piece of paper to say I'm going
to the store or I'm going for a jog or
something like that so it's very extreme
here and it seems we're on the up curb
so it's just getting worse in terms of
numbers but so there's this extreme
contrast between how wonderful my life
is right now I'm here with my family and
I'm doing I'm working remotely like like
you John and I I'm doing you know
physical work every morning and I'm
feeling much healthier than I have in a
long time actually and the grim picture
outside and my neighbor who's elderly
and just had a stroke and it's very odd
he can't really we're not supposed to go
and talk to her and so well usually we
have a relationship so so so there's
it's a very very extreme contrast
between me right now feeling like I'm
living my life like I would want to be
living white life really almost in a
retreat like a Buddhist retreat with my
family and and then the extreme
situation outside you know so that's
Andrew I just and I'm just this is a
practical curiosity but I've heard of
that I've heard I know this is true
Italy I didn't know that it was also
true of France that you need some kind
of you need effectively a permission
slip to go out and carry on your
business what what does that mean like
where do you get that is you you find it
on the internet and you have to print it
out and it has to have a
date on it so we've had our groceries
delivered so I haven't even gone out and
done that yet actually but but so I
guess you you can change the date each
time you go go out and you have to say
why you're going out if you're going out
to walk the dog or go for a jog you have
to be six meters away from other people
six meters something is something like
that maybe I've got that wrong I could I
couldn't have a but but you're supposed
to really keep a distance from everybody
I'm not allowed to go out with my family
for a lot for example I can go it alone
I could go for a jog and I could do
exercise or go for a walk but but but
again I'm in a little village so I'm not
in the heat of the the the the heat of
the thing which a lot of my friends in
Paris are and I can kind of I can feel
that from them that it's very intense I
think being stuck in a small apartment
would be would be pretty hard yeah you
know so I read your papers your paper
today much too quickly i'm gonna i'm
going to reread it in more more detail
here is called gnosis in the second
person responding to the meaning crisis
in the Socratic quest of authentic
dialogue so what struck me in the end is
is and please correct me if I'm wrong if
I've misunderstood something because I
this is a big overview so this is about
dialo goes right and you outline sort of
five dimensions of dialogue owes and one
is the let's say person to person which
is the horizontal dimension of dialogue
us me talking to you and then the
vertical dimension which is about
talking to to being about questioning
yourself and/or your existence I guess
or being itself and then you talk about
how that
but that moves into something a third
dimension which is related to the eye
maybe the eye though in some level that
something is created out of this
dialogue hmm right and I and and then
the fourth dimension is that moves into
time and then the fifth dimension is a
kind of timelessness that results and so
so I like this whole model I think it's
very very beautiful and I wondered if
you could just go into detail and flush
it out a bit so I'll uh I'll start Chris
and I will probably tag-team a lot
because our thinking on this paper is
deeply symbiotic I think one thing is to
perhaps it would be useful to keep a
distinction in hand that we could refer
to throughout which is dialogo cesare
the process that's being realized and
dialectic is the psycho technology that
people can learn and practice in order
to try and realize the process and try
to cause it to be instantiated in a
dialogue and so part of what we're
trying to do in the paper is to figure
out as you mentioned the the dimensions
both phenomenological and functional of
d logos as a process and we're also
starting to that of course has merit in
its own right we're also doing that also
because we're trying to figure out from
the phenomenology and the functionality
what the psycho technology should look
like what should dialectic look like
what are some of the features that
should be put into practice and the hope
is the oral hope from the paper is if we
can work back from the phenomenology and
functionality of do logos into sort of
reverse engineering the dialectic we can
put that potentially into a deep
dialogue and I choose that term
intentionally a deep dialogue with what
we see in Socratic practice within the
Platonic dialogues and the Neoplatonic
traditions as a way of then putting all
of that into dialogue with
what's happening right now with the
emergence of both psycho technologies
like guys and stocks circling or you
know Atwood Russia's empathy circling or
Peter Lindbergh's
anti debate these new practices and
their attempts to tap into the
collective intelligence of distributed
cognition and so if we can
reverse-engineer dialectic put it into
contact with the historical scholarship
of platonic dialectic take that whole
thing and put it into dialogue with
these emerging practices in which people
are seeking to reformulate Andry vivify
dialogue so that it can be a means by
which people can cultivate wisdom in a
deep sense then we think what we can do
is help to bring philosophy a--
the cultivation of wisdom into these
emerging practices because I generally
see although I have great value and
appreciation and I participate in these
practices I'm not just an outsider of
great value and appreciation for things
like circling and I'm in constant
communication with guys hens Don and guy
actually sanctions this and in a
positive sense on what I'm about to say
I see these practices as largely lacking
the integration with philosophy ax and
that maybe means if can i interject a
little bit of lacking in thinking
lacking in a Nigerian yeah I think
you're in when we what Heidegger means
by thinking this is almost taboo in in
these kind of circles we're supposed to
have a we're supposed to work on our
feeling somatic experiences and then on
the other hand so there's this divide
between the somatic experience and
divided you semantically magnetism
yeah intellectualization and extreme
sort of empiricism on one hand and
extreme sort of experience on the other
am i Gary much very much I think that's
right I think there's kind of yeah
there's kind of a Cartesian
intellectualism
that's often the presentation of
propositional argumentation or there is
sort of that like I call it the semantic
romantic romantic ISM where somehow by
sort of exploring our somatic states we
will accrue to the good life that's not
to say that there isn't a lot of value
in mindfulness in at reception
you know I hold to all of that but I I
agree what's missing and I think you put
your finger on it well in a lot of these
practices where we're trying to
communicate and even commune if by that
we mean that the connectedness and
intimacy between people is also valued
what's missing and all in a lot of these
practices is like I said is but how do
they how do they help us cultivate
wisdom both individually and
collectively in a way that's seriously
needed for addressing the meaning crisis
now let Chris speak well that was pretty
comprehensive John the only thing I
would add to it is that in order to
affect the convergence between the more
the sort of the discwizard of dimension
of it and what we might call the more
characterological dimension of it is
that's why we've invoked the Socratic
exemplar positive your vocabulary always
just knocks me off my feet what is dis
quiz ative pls dis quiz ative meaning
the process of disquisition meaning sort
of the the explication
the the discussion for the purpose of
explication ratiocination that kind of
thing that that sort of oh guys know
that yeah yeah um so I mean the reason
that Socrates is such a choice symbol or
symbol on for us is precisely because
the Socratic dialogue goes combines the
dramaturgical dimensions of in the
interactivity of the process right the
actual felt somatization of the process
right the dimension of it that's played
through and dramatized and enacted and
then the dimension of it that then
regather zazz as a as a process of of
will be Maiko reasoning or rationing
right and so because because
Socrates as a symbol is both a entreats
us to both at once he entreats us both
to the to the the discourse for the
purpose of insight and discourse for the
purpose of for personal transformation
those two are then bundled in the
process of dialogo stripe because you
have what we called or what right called
the sensibility transcendence between
persons the disclosure the disclose the
social disclosure that avails insights
about one another and then you have in
in between the interest to sees of that
process you have the ontological
disclosure the thing that seems to avail
more of reality and that they're bundled
together and Socrates because of the
nature of the symbol because of his
countenance he tends to provoke both of
those states at once because Socrates
sort of stands Socrates is both a
personal and impersonal mystery right
and we don't know who that somehow who
knowing who Socrates is isn't just
knowing who Socrates is it's also
knowing who we are and knowing who we
are isn't just knowing who we are it's
knowing what what what the world is writ
large and all of these things seem to
constantly together in this cretak
symbol and that's why he's like the
prism through which all of this then
opens so that's why we've dropped him I
mean it's not exactly an ingenious move
Socrates has been this for a long long
time too many people we've dropped him
into the middle of this because he's so
he's he's an emissary and an exemplar
for it at same time right so he's a
bridge and he's sort of a bridge between
the per the personal and the impersonal
going back and forth and he also
transcends both the personal and the
impersonal well he famously famously
presents himself as a tip-offs not
belonging to any category and as
Mattacks who somehow between the human
and the divine and so he he consciously
or at least through in plato's dialogue
identifies with those two those two you
know buying the symbol long
relationships you have the binding
together he sort of sits between our
normal categories of identity for human
beings and as i said he sits between the
human
devine and therefore he can bind both of
those together a rock cows can his
really good book Heidegger's platonism
talks about why Socrates in the dialogic
form are actually inseparable this goes
back to Ashley R mocker and
Slagle from the presentation of what of
Plato's view of of the cultivation of
wisdom and the basic the basic idea is
and it's it I think it actually comports
a very well conversion with the argument
that Chris and I are making but trying
to get dialogue activating and
integrating all the four kinds of
knowing in that what we see in the
dialogue you need some you need three
things you need argumentation obviously
mm-hmm in order to do as Chris said
provoke those kinds of profound insight
it has to be a kind of an argument ation
directed towards the affordance of
aporia right that that way you're you're
forced to step back and wonder in a
profound way to call yourself into
question and think about Heidegger we
are the beings whose aporia is means a
sort of a state of unknown entity yeah
that's like a net right yeah deep deep
perplexity and an epidemic precipice
okay so he pushes you a little bit
towards the precipice and then you stand
back and you experience wonder and
everything comes into question and
therefore you you you actually identify
with what Heidegger would call design
you identify with that aspect that seems
to be central to human beings how we are
the beings whose beings are in question
and that gives us a privileged kind of
access in our being not enough not in
our self or oh yeah but a nurse analogy
but but beyond that not yeah not just in
our propositional thoughts but in in
that deeper kind of thing we're talking
about earlier the thinking and so that
of course it is centrally or the
argumentation but you but what you you
don't have just a competition of
arguments right in the dialogue you also
the competition of ways of life Seifer
do you have to represent a way of life
he represents the unexamined life that
is right sorry the examined life is
living in competition so you're not only
having arguments in competition you need
to see ways of life in competition
with each other and I think yeah I
continue your thought you let I just
well make the third point and you can
choose how you wish to respond and so
Socrates exemplifies the competition
between arguments that is supposed to
induce wonder in the insight that Chris
mentioned he's supposed to he you can't
do this with argumentation you have to
in order to represent the competition
between late ways of life you have to
rely on drama that's so the does be
embodied and yeah you have to have that
right so how are you gonna get argument
and drama together you need dialogue and
then the next thing you need right is
you need you need Socrates represents
aspiration he represents our
relationship to our sacred second self
he represents a call to transformation
and transcendence right and that call to
to any that's another reason why has to
be symbolic for us that call to self
transcendence right that's there has to
be you you need a form of thinking
that's inherently woven with symbol it
has to it has to both reach you where
you are but draw you beyond where you
are it has to do a dues it has to it has
to be the Midwife for you and so the
dialogue is also the way in which you
represent that aspirational relationship
right it's in the back and forth between
you the interlocutors and Socrates that
you can see the aspirational movement
taking place the dial up think that the
fact that the dialogues are like they're
non completable they're open-ended
they're often emergent is exactly
required for representing what Plato is
trying to talk about so the so I'm
trying to say there's these three deep
ways in which Socrates exemplifies the
necessity of dialogue for the
cultivation of wisdom hmm okay you were
talking about the examined life in the
unexamined life okay yes and so as you
were saying that what came to me right
now is the event that we're all
experiencing which seems to be in the
background of all of our discussions
even if we're talking about
you know philosophical high abstract
philosophical things Oh
and so so I want I want I want to
somehow make a bridge to what's going on
in the world right now and and the
examined life and and what that means in
the face of this extraordinary thing
that's happening in the world
coronavirus or whatever and how this can
and also how this can help us in terms
of this dialogue oh so in terms of
making life more meaning through
dialogue goes how can we relate that to
our actual experience right now you do
you have anything to say well I do I
want to give I want to relate a quick
story and it will directly concerns
Chris and that way I can segue to Chris
yes I wondering what he was just because
Chris and I have been talking about this
at length and I want I want him to take
over a little bit on this but I had
another meeting with online virtual
meeting somebody was interviewing me
about the meeting crisis and we were
talking and we were talking at one point
and I said I want to be very careful
with the language and he said and he
picked up on that knee and he's like any
know that he really liked that and and
then he and then I said you know you
know and then I pointed to Chris and
Chris's gift his great gift for being
both you know capable of a precision of
expression that is at the same time
beautiful and beauty is one of the ways
in which we aspire right this is a
platonic idea and then you know that I
pointed to Kristin but that because
they're stripped I was trying to say how
that precision and beautification of
thought is so needed and he had this
response spontaneous and beautiful he
said of course I would he said this
literally he said I would rather die
than not talk like that and I'm using
this example because it's very pertinent
in the middle of this crisis and he says
to me right he says it very since earth
I'd rather die than not be
to talk that way and then I said to him
that's you I said you know you've said a
lot but that's the Socratic moment for
me that's we that's where you get it not
in thought but you get it in yourself
like you're being right that the
unexamined life is not worth living and
there's something about that and you
know and notice that the context the
language he used and the context in
which Socrates offered that Socrates was
facing death the person that I was
talking to he is you know he's he's
facing the situation you're referring to
Andrew and that's that comes out from
him naturally and spontaneously they're
right and so they're there there is
obviously you know there's a sense in
which we're jumping up and down Maslow's
hierarchy of needs right now and people
have to take care of their survival but
there's a point at which right there's a
point at which people also need a
meaning to a difficult difficult
situation in fact in the most difficult
of situations the most threatening of
situations they are willing to put mere
survival at risk in order to try and
maintain an examined and meaningful life
beyond as I said Chris came readily to
my mind about that deep connection and
readily to my lips about that deep
connection between the capacity for
making meaning and that ability to
revivify and you know empower the the
entirety of one's psyche yeah please
speak to that Chris because I think
that's my experience of both you guys
actually and that's why I want to talk
to you I think you both have that drive
thatthat kind of almost monomania which
which which wouldn't wouldn't wouldn't
couldn't bear on some level to be living
a life that wasn't that didn't have
authenticity but also a kind of striving
towards beauty at the same time
sorry to keep talking crisp please say
something yeah well I'm kind of hot at
the collar thank you John and I don't
it's tit I don't feel equals those
estimations so maybe I'll just glide
over them I'm touched by it I just don't
know what to say to it I think so I
think there are some interesting things
happening that I've been noticing both
personally and then in personally I was
telling John that I had I had a strange
episode maybe a week ago or so there I
felt there's really no other way to put
it I just sort of felt the gulf open up
beneath me and the sense of futility and
I and I mean I'm a damn it this
attribution I think at the time I think
what I think now was a midget
misattribution of any number of personal
failings or personal doubts and I think
what it actually was is it had something
more to do with the super personal
nature of what's going on right now but
I was effectively enclosed by feelings
of futility that were tera lytic like a
torpor just something that I couldn't
move from I remember what I went up
three hours on a three-hour walk just to
try and shake it off and didn't manage
to do it and I just sort of lingered for
a couple of days and then slowly over
time it unwound enough for me to regain
some ability and to get back into
activity but I was puzzled by that
because I never I never I'd never
experienced something that I found such
a difficult time sourcing that seems so
diffused whose locus was nowhere and
everywhere at the same time and the
diffuseness of that feeling is precisely
what marks this crisis it's a property
of virulence in general and because of
that virulence is such an easy host for
meaninglessness just as the BIOS is host
for a virus right it MX the analogy of
meaninglessness precisely because we
can't source it properly
and it reminds me of I think it was
Hegel who talks about the distinction
between truth and certainty and that the
scientism of the president has collapsed
them together and I think what may
happen now and potentially this is you
know some kind of chaotic you are
talking about this John is a kind of
chaotic opportunity and perhaps it is we
might hope so that with the ebbing of
certainty comes a renewed interest in
truth yes in a way that can effectively
dissociate itself from the from the from
what I think is ultimately an erroneous
synonym 'ti right they are not the same
thing fundamentally they cannot be and
while that distinction might not
completely disappear as a consequence of
the crisis at least there might be some
tremors sort of laid to the foundations
of that misconception and if that
happens enough for us to take notice
it's as the at like it's as though we're
citing a familiar script and we recite
it like an epistrophe we recite it over
and over and over again but then all of
a sudden it's like a seizure and there's
pausing script a pause long enough for
us to hear a moment of silence through
it it's like is the credit this limit
it's like a Socratic aporia and a
repetitive aporia and if we can if we
can get a foot across the threshold of
the aporia and hold it in place long
enough to listen to listen into the
silence into the silence of the sapore
then there might be something in behind
and in between that silence that becomes
something life-affirming and life-giving
I mean you're but I'm not but you're
both or are or were at some point
Buddhists I can't help think of Shunyata
alright groundlessness thus comes to
mind
um just groundlessness which is another
sort of translation of Shunyata so I was
thinking right right right and so but
then the transmutation of that empty
vacuous nothing listen to the stream now
at the the sness of the you know is
that's a transmutation that we're not
we're not adequately educated and
trained to know how to make right we
don't know how to alkalize our feeling
of aimlessness our feeling of vacuous
'no Swee don't know how to chemic
we transform that into something that
seems pregnant and electric and it's
that kind of training that we need right
now and so you know those people who are
equipped and I'm not saying I'm one of
them because I don't feel at all like I
am but those people who are equipped to
be able to step into the Fisher that's
opened by that boy by that void and then
to to present it properly to everyone
and to reveal the affordances that it
has the potential to cede us like that's
what that's what we need right now and
this could be I mean you know all the
dudes saying abound that we're hearing a
lot of it's justified perhaps some of
its not but but what it could be
is it could be the opportunity for
intervention for a philosophic
intervention like philosophy has to come
out of its semi-retirement now and
resume its all post on the frontier and
if it can do that this might actually be
an opportunity the likes of which we've
never seen in our lifetimes I don't know
I mean that could be revealed to be an
exclamation and a few weeks when all of
this settles down who knows but that's
the way I feel at the moment hmm well I
was just talking with my wife at dinner
time and we were talking about all of
the institutions that have are sort of
be coming into question at this point I
mean school medicine you know government
the hole the hole all of the structures
that we rely on or that we don't
necessarily like but that we we we we
work with unthinkingly they're not
collapsing but they're all being put
into question yeah all of them which
which just is it's a remarkable moment
in that sense another thing that's been
called into question is when this is
something that Kurt Agard was said had
to be put into question that we were
going to wake up his existential beings
his common sense busyness right living
our lives according to the obvious nests
of common sense and the busyness of our
day to day projects my hand and
kirkegaard said you know and to
you and until you can wake up from that
and and he was deeply influenced by
Socratic aporia he wrote his
dissertation on Socrates and Socratic
irony until you can wake up from that
then there's a sense in which she can
never come into an authentic kind of
being and so I think and do I would take
your point I would deepen it by saying
that the way it's impacting on the
minutiae of our life as well not to not
to dismiss but to include as well as the
way it's impacting on sort of the
overarching you know the the gods of our
you know the institutions of our society
I think it's also important to note the
way it's impacting on the minutiae of
our life and therefore having the
capacity to wake us up from common-sense
obvious 'no sand the busyness and the
things that seem to be undeniable that
turn out to be actually quite deniable
like shopping yeah there's shopping and
like like going to school and like going
to work the most basic things right yeah
that john i have to sorry for
interrupting but when you were talking
about what Kierkegaard says about this
I'm reminded of an anecdote I think it's
I mean often sumata or where it is but
it's somewhere in his corpus of work
that and this is where this is where the
importance of good humorists I think
coming to effective at moments like this
but there's a there's a there's a little
anecdote where he says that and that
this is a fictitious and apparent to the
fifth but that you know he was going
about his business on the streets of
Copenhagen and he saw a man he saw a man
a busy man of his affairs was so
preoccupied with his busyness that he
had his head cast down walking around
going about his errands and he was run
over by a carriage and Kim Garst said I
laughed I laughed I laughed I laughed I
laughed because he was just so busy and
I mean you know he has a he has a
slightly slightly invective sense of
humor perhaps but I think the point in
here is that certain absurdities of our
of our everyday are now being revealed
in Contra right now and it's going to
take some good humorists and
Ernests like him to be able to spot them
and to represent them to us properly
I find myself laughing at myself for the
things I take very seriously and putting
them into question you know but also
what gets revealed is the stuff that
should always be taken seriously like
the things that people aren't
questioning are the things that they are
retreating to almost like the way you're
supposed to take refuge in the Sangha or
the Buddha and the Sun and the Dharma
right they're taking refuge in those
practices and those those people that
give them you know the senses of
connectedness to themselves to each
other into reality they people are
withdrawing into the Citadel of whatever
religio they're capable of generating
and maintaining that's clearly the case
the monastery is coming to everybody's
home or something it's like it's back
and and it's that well you know you
you've you fate you face the life of a
cop right because police have lives that
are 90 percent boredom shot through with
ten percent terror and so most of us are
facing that right now you know many
people are talking about you know
they're shut inside and they don't know
what they're gonna do with themselves
and on one hand they're facing this
tremendous kind of boredom and then but
then of course every now and then they
lift their eyes towards the window and
they're filled with a kind of terror and
the thing that modifies both of those
that enhances your capacity to find well
meaning in the face of boredom because
mortal boredom is sort of a mini meaning
crisis right and and the thing that
allows you to confront terror with
courage is is precisely your capacity
for cultivating meaningful relationships
with yourself with other people and with
the world and so the people who I think
are starting to sense this as not just a
momentary
disruption because that's not what it is
we should stop pretending that's what it
is this is a long-term thing we're
facing and the end and Jordan Hall and I
talked about this in a couple of recent
videos this is not going to be the only
pandemic all other conditions that cause
lists have not changed in the world in
fact if anything they're going to keep
increasing we're gonna keep melting the
permafrost we're gonna keep cutting down
the rainforests we're gonna keep
increasing our you know our travel and
our trade in grow in accelerating rates
this is gonna happen again and it's
gonna happen again
and so the people who are starting to
realize that this is could be something
as game-changing could not maybe not
this time but I'm but with increasing
frequency the probability of this
happening is gonna go up dramatically
we're facing something like what the
Black Plague did to Europe in the Middle
Ages and how it completely altered the
worldview the sense of agency and arena
that people had in a profound and
irreversible manner I think we're facing
that I'd like I say maybe not this
pandemic but I would predict within the
next one that's what this is maybe a
minor pandemic for one thing young
people are not dying you know absolutely
terrible that elder people are dying but
I think in the Spanish flu killed more
people than olive oil longer or one or
something so back in having that every
five years yeah there's another thing
that's been kind of interesting about
this interesting and interesting in a
perverse way but our relationship to
time which already has been affected in
the way that Han talks about right the
third the aimless wizzy of time right
the effect that that has in our ontology
is also changing as a consequence of
that so for instance I find it
incredible in the proper meaning of that
term that a month ago or just over a
month ago I was I was traveling around
and I was in Italy for maybe about 10
days and then I came back you know
through a couple of its larger airports
more or less carefree coronavirus had
started at that point to permeate
consciousness but not knowing that it
has now and and certainly there was no
ordinance to self isolate when I got
back that was just over a month ago
the world has changed utterly since then
and and the the fact that such change
could be so comprehensive and so
instantaneous and every day every day
there's it's like there's this deepening
recurrence that makes the virus feel
cyclical like almost purgatorial right
see cuz for many of us has dwelled in
our consciousness for only a matter of
weeks and already it's starting to feel
inexorable and interminable like we've
been living with it for an eternity and
yet it's only been a few a few weeks so
the way that it leaders the way that it
rests on our consciousness seems not to
track our typical experience of time so
I think our our ontology of passage of
ours is also changing because of that
too and so you and the realization that
you were talking about John of the
transitory yielding to something
indefinite I think a lot of people
haven't quite crossed that threshold yet
but some people have and I think that
when a quick critical mass crosses that
threshold that terror is the thing of
all of all of the systems right economic
educational health etc of all of the
systems that are affected by this the
one that I'm most apprehensive about is
what happens when the critical mass
starts to realize that this may yet be
an indefinite state of affairs and that
our relationship to the world with the
fifth like the physiognomy of the world
the countenance of the world is slowly
slackening it's slowly starting to look
crestfallen and when that physiognomy
completely goes slack and loses its
confidence that's when that's like I'm
worried about it's like a judgment or
something it's like the last judgment
like I'm sorry to bring that up but I'm
thinking at all it's I think of like
some people are fully prepared in the
sense they're spiritually preparing
themselves and they have been for a long
time and other people will be just
totally unprepared I mean some people I
guess there's degrees of preparedness
but but but it almost feels like it
almost feels like this apocalyptic
biblical moments or something and but
notice that could notice that answer
notice that I think it's on Paul
recently I haven't seen the video yet
Paul vindicated one on whether or not
this is a judgment of God oh I just saw
it it's fantastic
I don't like that's wonderful that's
really good though I imposed is it so
insightful II yeah well he always does
that that goes other question so what I
wanted to say Andrew is notice how we
are starting to shift and of course all
of the and and and it should continue by
the way all of the political
socio-economic and most importantly the
medical language is still rolling but
already the mythological language is
struggling to come to the fore and you
invoked it spontaneously Andrew Paul's
already invoked it it's part of his job
to invoke their thoughts and I mean that
as a compliment
does any thoughts appalled right and one
of my concerns one of my concerns is and
I was talking to this about Chris is
that there's a pattern that could could
potentially emerge in which this gives
an initially a spike in a sense of
meaningfulness and I was talking also
with this with Peter Lindbergh because
when you can invoke those terms
seriously imagine being a imagine three
three months ago trying to invoke
judgment God's judgment and the
apocalypse right seriously and everybody
would have their eyes would have large
like me Chris and I've seen this when we
try to talk to people about this you're
always sort of glaze over and I'll you
know but notice how now you can say that
right you know it all sincerity and you
can expect reasonably so to be taken
seriously so that mythological language
is coming out
and notice what could i khalaf i it a
little bit okay it please that's why
you're saying I'm sorry I interrupted I
didn't I don't want to miss attribute
everything to you but I just wanted to
say that you know I think what's what's
happening for a lot of people is that
you know the the virus right it's it's
it's it's taken on the mythological and
I mean that the sense I'm trying to
articulate the mythological role of like
an Old Testament deity
the demonic chaotic aspect is out of the
blue unpredicted reality that will do
what it will do remember God's name I
will be what I will be right the the the
nameable thing that comes in and it's
ubiquitous like some sort of spirit and
you don't know who who has been taken by
it and who hasn't and it seems to be
falling as a judgment but you're not
sure what the judgment is and it seems
to be potentially assuring in a new a I
mean these this is a way of thinking
that you know is strongly associated
with like Old Testament deities and and
the thing about that is is the problem I
see with that is that has a lot of
potential danger associated with it as
the mythological meaning we try to bring
to bear uh-huh yes and so that's why I
maybe I interjected tumeric prematurely
and I apologize for that but I think
this is nevertheless an important point
to bring up well I want to say I want to
say that I don't think I wasn't
suggesting this is some kind of
punishment of God or any of that
nonsense like III that's that's
grotesque to me as a way of thinking
right what what it what it feels like
more is that some people some people are
going to suffer meaninglessly and other
people are going to you know have a
deeper experience of life after such an
event but why the term judgment then
because yeah it just came to me when he
was talking and he and and and I was I
was thinking of the the Old Testament
and I was thinking of this the final
days and all this sort of stuff where
some people make it into the kingdom of
heaven and other people don't so that's
not and that's not that's more
existential than and and I wouldn't want
to ascribe any kind of no no theism to
that even you know no I wasn't trying to
do that that's why I was very careful to
use the word myth you know what I'm
saying is right that language came very
naturally to you and what's what's
important is exactly the point you just
made you don't you don't hold to any of
the metaphysics
behind that language but nevertheless
that those images that have been woven
into our culture come spontaneously to
mind and I don't think that's happens
thanks Andrew I think that's gonna
happen for a lot of people in a lot of
ways in a lot of circumstances and that
is risky because that's the kind of
thinking that can mobilize people in
whatever even some pretty weird ways
yeah yeah and so I think you can sort
cults and cults and prophetic calls the
cleansing and purity and purification is
that language so far away from where we
are now it's not that far no no it's not
because I mean already into certain
forms of social intimacy are already
appropriate so actually no purity purity
codes abound right now and they may well
they may well persist in that direction
but I was going to say to Andrew that I
think that the the instinct to find a
certain amount of reflexivity to see a
reflection of ourselves born in the form
of the virus even though even if we're
not even if we're not subscribing to the
metaphysics behind behind behind divine
judgment if we're if it's done very
carefully the fact is that there is
something about the virus that is going
to pronounce and surface something that
is already implicit in our experience of
meaning right that's the whole point of
it being an analogic host for the
meaning crisis is that it is surfacing
like as a cathodic force bursting up
from the unconscious if you will it is
surfacing something that's already
present that's already present to us
that's already implicitly present to us
so obviously you know we have to be very
careful about metaphysical attributions
but using the virus as a dialectic way
of confronting our meaninglessness is
where thee is where the pedagogical
opportunity of this comes from right not
simply to to wave it away to the
to the to the you know to the random
cruelty of nature even if that's what it
is fundamentally but rather not to pay
attention to what it - what it reveals
about our our the relationship or
ontology right that's not and that's not
a divine attribution necessarily but
it's it's taking the emergence of it to
be to be a symbolic affordance for
communing with ourselves yeah
individually and as a culture well I was
listening to this rabbi speak about it
and if you were if you were an Orthodox
rabbi and you believe that everything
that happened was God right you you
would think that this also is God right
and this is a divine thing that's
happening uh-huh because the Messiah is
coming and and and therefore you you
just have to keep sort of living your
life in in celebration and it's not that
oh this is this judgment and you're
being punished or or anything like that
that was the feeling I got from him as
like a person of faith and how they see
this and that doesn't take away from any
of the you know the pain and the
suffering and all that it's just I don't
know if I'm being very clear and what
I'm trying to say so it's almost the
opposite of what John was saying about
judgment is that it's not that people
are being judged
it's that reality is coming in and if
you were religious you would say divine
reality is here you know this is divine
reality I mean I'm okay with using the
word divine maybe you want to see sacred
but well I want to respond to that
because ishi I think what I'm saying is
we face a choice and I think the word
you invoked is the word that you know
Jordan Hall and I are talking a lot
about which is what does faith mean now
and what does it and is there is there a
sense of faith that can put us into the
the kind of situation we're in where
we're not talking about faith as the
attempt to bring about closure the
temp to two to reestablish and I'm using
Chris's sense of this word uncertainty
but faith is right because these are
these are you know and this is this this
is the fear I was trying to articulate
with the potential mythological
resurgence of sort of a demonic deity
the deities that will promise a
certainty and closure and purity and
protection right and that's I take that
as a very serious threat and I think one
of the responsibilities I feel now and
I've been privileged to work with Jordan
with that and also with Chris but two
videos with Jordan is well there's an
alternative way of understanding faith
that doesn't mean that seeking for
closure and completeness and purity and
perfection but instead is about a kind
of it's a cultivated sense of being that
gives you a continuity of contact with
things as they unfold so that you can
evolve with them and you have a sense of
the course of that so that you are
sensitive to Kairos and you can
participate in it in in with effective
agency that sense of faith rather than a
if you'll allow me this word a worship
based a sense of faith which is what I
was trying I'm trying to pull these two
things apart I'm not trying to deny
anybody their worship I you know what
that I don't do but what I'm trying to
say is for those of us who don't find
any kind of nostalgic return a viable
option and I would really really hope we
don't turn back to a demonic deity
answer um then we do need to re
articulate we need to bring up into
dialogue and into dialectic the kind of
faith that we started this discussion
with the faith that Socrates has when he
says the unexamined life is not worth
living how does he get that it's not
certainty in the way that two plus two
equals four it's not certainty but it's
a it's a he's in he's been he's lived
his life there's been continuity of
contact with an unfolding disclosure of
being that has vouchsafe to him what a
meaningful life is and he's sensitized
himself
and acquired that tastes deeper and
deeper and that's the kind of faith I
want to try and bring out the kind of
faith that is in measurably in meshed
with dia logos and that's what I'm Trump
that's why I brought up that whole
concern that I had is that I don't want
any of that that mythology that tends to
like try to total eyes and shut down and
you know bring about the the closure and
the the completeness and the purity and
the perfection but we need to resist
that temptation and I'm gonna use that
biblical sounding word deliberately and
and the way we can resist it and it's
not just like trying to hold it off we
have to beautify and fall in love with
if you'll allow me Socratic faith as a
contrast to that that that that I don't
know what they call it that demonic
faith hmm Socratic faith and demonic
faith okay I I think the other John that
there's also there's also a way in which
the Socratic faith the disposition of
Socratic faith can carefully and perhaps
are collectively but maybe on a
person-to-person basis the Socratic
faith can be applied as an attitude an
interrogative attitude to foster
dialogue with the motifs with the
demonic motifs that instinctively
surface at times like totally keep going
but I just want to say right I agree
that's a really good point that's a
excellent point because there's no
there's no stopping the perfusion of
those of the of those kinds of motifs I
mean they're they're they're baked so
thoroughly into us at this point that
we're not going to be able to wave them
away or turn resolutely away from them
and ignore them but we are going to have
to find a way to bring them into our dye
to enfold them into the dialectical
process and and I'm thinking very much
in a in a sort of a union careful
calibrated Union descent into the
contents of the impersonal unconscious
right and that's exactly what the whole
process is about it's it's it's you know
I see I see you I see you motif and I
raise you you know let's let's well that
was worried about with with just staying
in this exercise
mode of angst and and that kind of thing
is that we have to dive into these I
don't know into the symbolic world on
some level and and and that takes a kind
of faith as well right yeah it does we
need we need to know how to turn the Old
Testament demon back into a Socratic day
Damon
Socrates has Damon and IIIi think
Chris's correction of my point is
completely correct and and wonderful and
and it's like the dialectic and that's
the pure dialectic that is expressing
here that we can't get stuck on this one
mode right Yee
apologies I interrupted you again it's
it's about how about I have when I get
accept we're all interrupting each other
it's fine I just okay
I just wanted to totally ignores I think
what Chris just did there was like not
only correct I think an example as you
pointed out Andrew I think very astutely
it exemplifies the very thing we're
trying to bring to the fore yeah there's
a way Chris is right I think there's a
way of addressing my concern but like I
say in a process of conversion and
transformation rather than a simple
process of exclusion I was falling prey
to the very thing I was criticizing I
was trying to trace remove decode and
keeping keeping something at bay which
is exactly the wrong thing to do so well
we could think of a non-theistic mode of
looking at the last at the Last
Judgement story or any of the old
stories and a testament like but they're
not there to be understood in some
absolute as you saying closed sort of
way right they're there to be worked
worked at and looked at as a piece of
sort of as a transparent window into
reality of some some kind the trick is
to keep them to I mean to keep enough of
the of the demonic within the demonic so
that it can challenge us and shake us up
because if we we need to be we need to
get into a place where we are open to
being surprised and shaken up because
that's what we're now facing going
forward in my estimation facing and and
if we my
we try to domesticate this with the
demonic that's my concern but I like
Chris's idea that entering into a kind
of Union dialectic wicket so that we can
transform it into the socratic demonic I
think that's I think that's a brilliant
insight Chris I think that's excellent
I personally idea of bringing young and
Socrates together because Socrates on
his own feels very dry to me and young
young is so rich nominal logically they
make they make a wonderful marriage of
heaven and hell well Chris and I are
gonna be working on a paper on that
actually probably for probably like
Monday right top of mind for us no I'm
just gonna say I like the way that
you've um I like the way you've you've
pinned it to a cat for his job to turn
the demonic to the dynamic I think is oh
I like that as a nice pissy turn
phrasing yeah well thank you so I I was
I was trying to get a turn of phrase
that captured the turn of your insight
so one thing that's been very
interesting for me to see in this
process it's funny I'm normally not much
of a news junky but of course I've
probably like most of the rest of the
world I've become one in these these
last days and sorry in the most recent
days I don't mean these last days maybe
that was a Freudian slip
I don't but but one thing that's been
really interesting and I mean we've you
know we've talked nauseam right now
about about what the the diminishment of
our wisdom institutions has done in a
longer term for our culture but one
thing that we're really seeing right now
I find it fascinating you know every day
when the politicians come out of their
their sanctum and have to address the
public and they they're forced into a
position of having to give platitudes
and having to give reassurance and aside
from just the practical and logistical
messages that they have the issue
they're also voiced with the demand of
bringing calm and bring
perspective now it's one thing to bring
calm to say you know folks we're doing
the best we can we've got it under
control but you can see them struggling
and I actually have I have sympathy for
them in this respect because that's
fundamentally it's it's it's in excess
of their role it's beyond their office
or at least it ought to be arguably it's
beyond their office to bring perspective
to bring philosophic perspective to
what's going on but because we don't I
mean obviously for those beholding to a
certain faith and worship you know they
they round on their their clergy etc but
for those for now a sizable I mean
majority in the West maybe minority in
the world but still a sizable minority
in the world who don't have those
offices to turn to we're rounding on our
politicians to give us if you give us
that perspective and there's I mean and
they obviously don't have it that's not
to say individuals among them can't be
insightful I'm sure they can but as an
office they just that's not a and that's
not the office they hold and I think
what we're starting to see right now is
we're starting to see that the gap the
vacuum the absence of the wisdom
institutions is particularly pronounced
at a time like this
you mean the separation of church and
state is is is is showing up as being
sort of schizophrenic
yeah well the church part is that is in
some ways absent altogether I mean not
they're not they're not but but for for
many of us you know we're our first
instinct is not in fact to look to
church leaders for perspective and and
we obviously look to our politicians to
give us the practical information we
need to know our business but between
those two things there is so fundamental
chasm within which we we we have only
ourselves to rely on but but this is
again where the context and this way you
have to have to be the dialogues with
the drama in the context
Socrates right you have to remember that
when we're reading these dialogues where
they set their set Athens is literally
under siege people are walled in they're
locked down the city is under sees the
Athenian Wars going there has been a
massive plague Pericles has died right
you know there's all that stuff is often
the context surrounding right the both
the dramatic context within which
dialogues are set in the historical
context in which Plato writes them and
they're originally presented Socrates is
very much he's not foreign to the
situation we are talking about
he is birthed out of it he is there in a
situation as you know as challenging as
threatening as we are in and that's why
it is again the practice that he's doing
within that context that is not
happenstance that is not happenstance
and and again you know and he's he's
trying to steal his way steer his way
between you know various you know
political skill and Charybdis as as
Athens careens around trying to find a
political solution to what many people
are now saying was ultimately you know a
cultural and you know a meeting crisis
for ancient heaven and he's supposed to
exemplify who we are supposed to be yes
moment is what you're saying yes and and
it's supposed to be Socrates or that's
what we're supposed to be doing we're
supposed to choose the life the
meaningful life the life with later
because the choice really Andrew I mean
and that's what came out when I was
talking to ethos this this morning right
the choice really I mean initially
initially first you know Maslow's
hierarchy mean yes I get it ischl either
the choices live don't die yeah but but
that is not a sustaining choice the
choice is ultimately are you are you
living is it a good life you living
right is it is it a life worth living
III well this is somewhat personal but I
decided and I've chosen and I've
committed to it I don't if it comes to a
point where I have to sort of start
violating the fundamental principles by
which I live in order to merely survive
I rather and I mean this I would rather
die I do not am I my own survival is not
as valuable to me as the principles that
I that that you know that Ivan that I've
inherited from Socrates that the
unexamined life yeah exactly
mm-hmm yeah yeah he's at some point
people
well sorry I'm speaking I'm over
generalizing for my case out of hope
maybe miss borne hope but I suspect that
many people will come to where they
night might need to consider that right
mm-hmm
and if I can come back to the judgment
again if you forgive me judgment is is
maybe you live maybe you'll die but the
judgment is really being able to say to
yourself that you've had a life worth
living
yes so it's not it's not an imposed
judgment of some helpless person uh-huh
who doesn't have any say in what's going
on it's it's okay did I have judging am
I good you judge it we judge ourselves
right we we are judging ourselves not
the final judgment is is is is really
it's it's it's some gods on its from the
depths of Gotham you know the being
whose being is in question okay and
ultimately have to we and we ultimately
have to live that question as deeply as
possible and and the way you live a
question is by turning it into a quest
nothing else you have to be open right a
quest is an open journey towards
continual revelation right and and I
just I think that what's gonna happen
once the the endurance aspect of that
once the emergency aspect of this is a
little bit more back rounded and the
endurance aspect comes out we have to
gonna have to endure for a long time I
think this question about the resiliency
of our of the meaning of our lives is
going to become more pronounced as
Christian and I think that's I think
that's the judgment that you and the
word in here means in French it means to
make hard right yeah you're something so
good point so there's a point where we
can't be made hard right
that's right one level we need to be
made you know strong but not hard
yeah yes well it's and yeah and that's
what the storks are trying to get right
again I have a meaning I've been
rereading some of releases meditations
and you were saying at the beginning of
this conversation John that well you
know what's gonna happen increasingly as
people are going to retreat to those
relations that constitute them in most
instinctively and and at one point at
one point Marcus Aurelius effectively
enumerates the sort of he enumerates
them almost as a trinity of relations
that ground our sense of being right one
is to the vessel that envelops us the
second is to the sort of the divine
cause that the source of all that
follows all beings and then the third is
to those that live alongside us and when
I think about that I that's that's
that's a very comprehending Trinity of
relations then that we can use as a way
of refocusing ourselves at from a ground
that is that is fundamentally deeper
than the one that we're used to treading
on and you're there you know the point
of living within the question of being
and questing after it is I think
precisely what you meant John by this
the definition of faith it's not closure
it's not the closing it's precisely the
opening it's the it's the opening of the
question that constitutes our being yes
it's the finite continually longing for
the infinite for the infinite is that a
strangle set yeah exactly and so the
point is it's it's the ongoing
receptivity to the emergence Jordan Hall
and I were both using the the the the
surfing and sailing metaphors right
where you're trying to set up outside of
kind of a passive empiricism or or an
overly active romanticism you can't
faith can't be in the imposition of your
will I'm just gonna make things happen
and faith can't be sort of the passive
waiting for the miracle that's going to
come and rescue you faith is like what
this what
with the what the with the skilled
sailor has it's the ability to receive
and adjust and evolve and ride the edge
of the wave in the storm you know as
Andy Clark's book has it you know
surfing the wave of uncertainty as we
need or that's the kind of faith I'm
talking about which is weather and the
recurring realization that we are ever
and always beyond ourselves that reality
is ever and always beyond the
predicaments that confine us to the
present yes I was saying that your
definition of faith is the same thing as
wit as your definition of wisdom faith
is wisdom in this in that sense yeah I
think so because because faith is
because it's because it's always
responding to reality and not shutting
down and yet being flexible enough to
you know be knocked over in your
sailboat and get up again and if if yeah
I would say if wisdom is connecting you
to the depths of your beings in the
depths of being so that you are
empowered that empowered nystagmus to
the depth that's the empowerment that we
I think we seek from faith it is to have
our participatory knowing so plugged in
to how things are unfolding that we can
participate as fully as possible yeah
it's a kind of also why understanding
that's good understanding it in in the
sense that you just meant to John
understand that's why power and
empowerment
unfortunately tainted though the word
now is politicized so the word now is
partaking of a something like an
exponent power I think for me is a much
handier way of understanding something
like it's a tonic form for that very
reason yeah like I guess I drew an
another way of bridging between the
meanings of faith and wisdom is that the
notion of reverence which is the ability
to you know to to sense the relevance of
that which is beyond you appropriately
to be appropriately fitted to that which
transcends your egocentric framework
and and give it a kind what what Iris
Murdoch calls a justice of attention
that you give an appropriate attention
you give it the attention it deserves to
the degree it deserves it knowing how to
do that is a profound kind of virtue
Woodruff in fact argues that a reverence
is a missing virtue for us so I would
sort of put these together as
overlapping and woven you know Islam
referencing and faith when you say when
you say reverence what comes to my mind
is worship and you hear you're rejecting
this idea of worship and and I'm sorry I
I think reverences not quite enough
because if you're revering something
you're still at a distance from it if
you're worshiping something or if you
find something divine if you're
something as sacred you're still at a
distance from it if something is divine
you know then if something if there's
something you worship then then you're
then you fall into it
well so that's just my no no like that
but I want to challenge you because I
might think the appropriate the way I
want to say that is that you know the
Socratic figure is actually supposed to
be the symbol on the sage is supposed to
be that which I mean that through which
we connect those we cross that distance
we don't collapse it we bridge a right
and and that's that's that's a different
thing and what I mean by reverence I
take your point well and I'm not trying
to invoke worship we should have
worshipped Socrates I think they'll be
ridiculous and you find horrifying but
why do we worship kind of we worship I
used to worship Leonard Cohen for
example you know or my gay friend
Alexander right worship Bette Midler and
say she was divine you see what I'm
trying to say them I'm trying to say
that that that there's yeah you're right
we're both right in a way like you're
right to say yes we need this sort of
bridge yeah but I think the bridge
collapse is that at a certain point when
when we're fully involved in what well I
think we should internalize the sage but
we should never be satisfied and that's
what I'm trying to get with
a sense of being being a feeling like
you're you you realized the relevance of
something right but that doesn't mean
you've you have you have conquered it or
consumed it like you we should
internalized I mean funnily the the
quote comes to mind which is really good
although it presents it in a negative
way is Nietzsche's quote about Socrates
he said I hate Socrates he's so close to
me I'm always fighting him now that's
not worship but that's reverence man he
like he Socrates is so close to him he's
always fighting him Socrates is this
deeply deeply internalized challenging
figure man and that's that's that's what
I'm thinking of right not that I so what
I think when I'm talking about reverence
I'm not I'm talking not about worship
I'm talking about that connectedness
exemplified in this age through this age
to something beyond this age that is
always going to be acknowledged to be
inexhaustible and beyond me what I'm
asking is the possibility of bringing
together intimacy and openness like you
should have with imagine somebody that
your that is your beloved right they are
close to you but you cannot enclose them
there's a difference there right and
that's what I'm trying to get I'm trying
to get that we have simultaneously the
with acknowledgement of how reality
withdraws and is beyond us but we can
nevertheless come into an intimate
flowing contact with it
so that's what I'm trying to get out
with it the notion of faith and
reverence
yeah I'm really not trying to articulate
a kind of worship or even putting off at
a distance but I don't also want an over
familiarization we need to keep the sage
and reality ultimately mysterious and a
tip-offs for us it's like a fire if you
get too close to it you get burned or
sight and so you got it you got to get
the Goldilocks zone where you're
intimate but the fire can still burn and
can still threaten you and say I mean
and this is why you know Greek myth
always pears the hero myth with the
hubris myth for all the myths of the
hero facing the challenge
right there's the hubris myth that don't
fly too close to the Sun right or don't
you know don't try and ride that the
chariot of the Sun or don't compete with
with act with with Athena for being the
greatest Weaver you have all of these
right hubris because the point is yes
you know we should have we should come
in too close you know contact with the
gods but you know in even Plato said
this you know you should you to try and
expect to live there all the time is is
a ridiculous concern and so that's what
I'm trying to get out with the notion of
reverence that's why there's an eros is
that there's always the tin generis
implicit in that reference because it's
precisely because the eros slacks
acquisition what they see in the thing
about eros is I mean this was it's a
mixture right it's both a lack and a
revelation and and Plato may differ and
you know in the symposium with Socrates
in eros how eros combines both of those
aspects together Russ wants us to draw
something into intimacy but eros should
also remind us of that which we always
lack and always will like right right
yeah exactly I guess so I guess that's
what I'm that's what I'm saying I think
that the air us like I I I understand
the difference between respect and
reverence as being that very difference
that one contains within it the
disposition of arrows and one
fundamentally does not yes
all right that's I think that's exactly
what I was trying to put my finger on as
long as we don't take just the current
meaning of eros no no of course not of
course is it there a place also for
worship though I'm still I'm holding on
to this thing because it's because I
don't know you you you if you're you you
worship let's say maybe you don't
worship the person themselves or the you
worship what they represent the you
worship the divine double or you worship
them hmm I don't know I guess it depends
what you mean by that word I mean I I've
already articulated that I think
philosophy is and this is a Socratic
Maxim is bound up with the combination
of a deep knowing of yourself and wonder
in which yourself is called into
question
you both coming engage on the project
and those are course and separately
bound up together
you can't deeply come to know yourself
and knowing yourself is always always
Socratic ly knowing the depths of the
world that you you belong to you can't
know yourself deeply unless you're also
capable of calling it deeply into
question and so Wonder and awe I think
are inseparable from this project I mean
I think Plato in fact is part of the way
you can understand his whole
philosophical project is to engage in
dialectic so that we we afford via logos
and do logos will deepen wonder into awe
and then aw is for its own sake because
oh is that that state where we're
getting sort of the depths of ourselves
and the depths of reality resonating
with each other and a really powerful
and and and in its moving of its own
accord it's not at the direction of our
egocentric projects or desires so I
think if you mean by worship a seeking
out of practices that induce ah that
that's fine I don't have any problem but
maybe that's not what you mean by
worship and so I see worship is what
draws you out of your ISA egocentricity
towards our and then you can leave
behind the worship once you've arrived
at the off but it's but it's a stage
it's a it's a it could be and then it's
very Buddhist so and and I'm trying to
remain open to this and see I'm even
crossing my arms instinctively because I
go up I was brought up on some
fundamentalist Christian and worship
doesn't meet what we're talking about
right now at all mm-hmm means a kind of
fruitless and I mean that deeply a
fruitless kind of self-sacrificing
towards a God who seems to be nothing
but a car a consummate narcissist who
needs endless praise and devotion while
telling us that we should never ever be
self-centered we should be like him but
what he seems to need more than anything
else is constant praise adoration and
worship and being put at number one no
matter what's happening at all costs in
all endeavors and I mean and I don't you
see and I feel privileged
to have experienced this in a negative
sense of privilege because if that that
I saw no good come out of that in
people's lives and it definitely hurt
and traumatized me in in powerful ways
and if that's what you mean by worship
then I yeah I I don't think that's what
I mean by worship is that many people do
mean that by worship many people sure do
I agree with you yeah mmm I take your
point
I'm sensing a lot of congruence between
what you're both saying I say I think
that there's there's a bit of a
terminological tension but I think
fundamentally what I'm what I'm getting
from you Andrew is that what you're
talking about with what you're meaning
by where it's correct me if I'm wrong I
think what you mean by worship is the
particular kind of relationship that the
person has with the symbol and and and
saying that the the particular
relationship that the person has with
symbol is precisely is precisely what
transfigure is the entire ritual into
some of the features that John is
describing the Wonder and the awe and so
you're talking about it in terms of this
the interpersonal connection between the
individual and the symbol that they're
attending to as opposed to the uniform
the perceptual opening that's evoked as
a consequence of that relationship
fundamentally they cannot collapse into
the same praxis and that's why I think
fundamentally the two of you were
talking about is it's not exactly the
same at least continues I think you're
right I think that's a good way of
putting it and maybe we could
distinguish it this way there's an
idolatrous sense of worship and there is
an iconic not in person in a carbon
sense I was thinking about I can't I can
eyes I'm like how you would worship an
icon if you were a Christian Orthodox
person you had worship this icon as
being as being a symbol of the divine or
yeah and that and that's exactly what I
meant by the sage it brings you close
but also beckons you beyond and he never
allows you to it brings you close but
never allows you to enclose and and if
that's what you mean by worship and I
think Chris is right Andrew I think he's
pointing to the convergence is exactly
right then I think that is a central
part of what we're talking about when
we're talking about Socratic faith
what's happening that what can emerge
when de Lobos emerges there's a deep
reverence it can be uh inspiring and it
may even become symbolic in that
worshipful way you're talking about but
what it shouldn't be and I think it's
what's clear Plato continually
undermines and what I had the invective
of from my own experiences it should
never become idolatrous worship I also I
also filled yeah I think that's well
said John I also feel I also feel
compelled to notice that for some even
though your particular experience of
ritual a Dori the ritual adoration of
Christ was idolatrous in the way that it
was forced on you for for many
Christians and I can't trap myself among
them but for many Christians I and I
trust this implicitly because I know
some of them very very thoughtfully for
for some Christians the adoration is an
iconic adoration and the way that we've
just described I I envy them that but
many of them many of them have that
experience for genuinely an example he
recorded know what I have the opposite
experience to John you know I grew up
without religion of any kind right so
everything you know I'm still very very
attracted to the esoteric aspects of
religion which lead into mystery and not
into this you know and and I'm very I'm
kind of critical about the clinical
Buddhists sort of where aspect of
Buddhism which doesn't have worship
which is is very let's say dry and
pseudo-scientific and psychological and
whereas I whereas and I'm also attracted
the Orthodox tradition because because
they there's this passionate aspect to
it but I can I can definitely see how
that can can go dark and and and can it
can be demonic and the opposite of
wisdom of any kind of yeah
but see what see what's happening here
see how I mean look what's happening
between the three of us yeah right the
deal logos the third factors emerging
none of us could have got here on our
own it's leading us in a way I'm finding
like things are being disclosed in a
powerful way and we're seeing how we're
inevitably being that into the depths of
religio and it's in its deep
relationship although not its identity
with religion as we're trying to grapple
with the situation that's confronting us
I think this is exactly yeah Chris and I
are talking about yeah I and I love how
what what I am what I find I agree
John and I think that one way I think I
think Corbin puts it this way he
correctly from wrong but I think that
one of the ways in which he phrases the
relationship of the individual to the
divine angel is that we are subjects of
the verb that is the divine angel and I
think that in the throes of diello go
like this I feel subject to a verb from
without in very much that way and and
you notice how your gesture was
automatic yeah I feel like I'm being
lifted up yes yeah and I'd be doing this
too like that being lifted up that uh
this is the point though Andrew mentions
notice how the horizontal is a meshed
inexorably with the vertical with a
vertical now the two are just deeply
interwoven and on all we can
analytically talk about them as
distinctive dimensions
notice how phenomenologically and
functionally they are so interwoven
together yes and then our relationship
to then to add the another dimension to
that that there our relationship with
our relationship right now with the
passage of time also changes yes when
we're deeply immersed in us yeah and
then also to add the next this
conversation notice how much I've been
alluding to other conversations and you
Andrew you and I have had conversations
and Andrew you and Chris are like so
that's that's where this particular
moment of dialectic is sitting in this
network of all these other conversations
that have this kind of meta dialogue
going on between them because they're
all informing and constraining each
other right now right here right now and
then this dialogue will go into that
network of constraints on further
conversations mm-hmm right right like
they're like they're all they're all
within the Neoplatonic circle right
they're all yeah I thought of indras net
but this acts perfect no I mean put
sense notion of indras net is is totally
correct because if you read the depths
of patinas he independently comes to
this exact same metaphor that each form
reflects all the other forms and they
mutually reflect each other well so I'm
not familiar with this can you can you
bring your business like in a fractal
way you mean what's the what's this
analogy which one is the net oh the net
is interest net is it's a Buddhist
scholar he he proposed the idea that
that like each each thing surrett the
word isn't quite right right but each
one every every hole on you could say do
you know this word hole on each each
part contains the hole or container or
something like that reflects its
photographic in that each the
individuality of each is just how it
determinately
reflects all the others so there's each
one is is right so this jewel is just
the reflection of all the other jewels
right okay okay so it's like whiteheads
notion of you know every moment is the
entire collapse of the universe so the
entire universe is collapsing to that
moment but that moment is included in
the collapse towards this moment and so
everything it's really everything is
mutually the toe Hannah yeah well yeah
and then that's then Platonists clearly
explicitly articulates that also of how
the forms are related to each other
within news so that's cool
yeah but what a beautifully woven
metaphor well what's cool for me is I
think it's it's sort of this holographic
deep learning because what it is is it's
in this holographic multi-dimensional
compression and variation function
everything is compressing and then
everything is varying but it's not just
sort of like in in a neural networks one
oppression one variation everything is
compressing and burying for everything
else and so reality is like this an
amazing amazing holographic deep
learning network yeah right well I was
also thinking about to be just slightly
more prosaic about about Zach when we
talked with Zach he said that this was a
jam and there were three of us yeah and
you know we started out I started off
having dyad like conversations with with
John and then conversation and now it's
become a triad it's become a like the
Jimi Hendrix Experience or something
well you know I'm being the drummer and
I'm a bit wild and and and and John is
is sort of keeping us together and very
passionate and Chris is maybe the bass
player it seems like it seems like a
kind of musicality and and that's that's
also what you're talking about when you
talk totally that's Christmas planning
yeah yeah this brought that metaphor to
the chapter we wrote in he played with
the musicality in me well Chris you
talked about it you know the in concert
metaphor that you that you made
throughout the chapter we just wrote
yeah yeah which is ironic because I'm
I'm in in my tactile life I'm not at all
very musicals but it seemed to me that
there was no more there was no more
perfect analogy to play into the process
because because because the idea of
being able to I mean because it because
it because it both because it's both
concentrated and distributed at the same
time because a melody can recur and
because a melody can transform and a
melody can be present in all kinds of
different ways yeah it's just a most
perfect go ahead John I just wanted that
to the metaphor now and your metaphor
you know and jamming you have to pick up
on it you have to pick up on it but you
have to get you have to get pick up on
it and get caught up in it right and if
you try and hold on to it too long you
destroy it
this is back again to this fate the
sense of faith you know you're you're
getting picked up on it your your the
continuity of contact you can continue
to play the serious
play and that's again the Socratic faith
so we could actually add that to the
two-year metaphor Chris I've also notice
notice that it starts off much more
intellectual or more prosaic and a bit
awkward and and in many directions and
then we build towards this kind of
Appeal is a factor it seems to happen in
all these kind of conversations least
ones I've been having we build towards
this we build up towards you know an
insight and a static insight of some
kind yep and I think that's the third
factor that we were talking about that
third factor where it takes on a life of
its own and it instead of you pushing
the conversation forward it takes on a
life of its own and everybody has drawn
up together forward in it that's the
third factor it's like it's the spirit
of the conversation it's the Geist yes
yeah you're taught you're spoken by the
conversation so transgenders yes ejected
sensation exactly this is why don't you
logos and dialectic are so central not
only to you know the the ongoing issue
of the meeting crisis but inter for
forgiving people the place and the
presence and the and and the in the
interlocutors ought to cultivate the
kinds of responses we need right now in
the face of what we're facing again
Socrates was in Athens during the plague
and while it was literally under siege
so we all have to be Socrates well yeah
in a way anyway we all else we only in a
way I'm sorry that felt very banal
actually a banal statement it felt like
a no no I'm sorry I what he's even now
advertising jingle or something well
yeah I don't want it to become
trivialize but I want I would want to
say we all have to become Socrates but
also in the way in which we all have to
become Siddhartha and we all have to
become loud say and perhaps if it's not
too sacrilegious given my previous
invective but also have to become Jesus
I mean you have to recover Socratic
wisdom and faith we have to recover that
Jesus is agape we have to recover loud
says-- flow we have to
recover you know sit harvest capacity
for profound transformative the insight
we need all of these now we needed all
of these and if art you know if our
musings about this stand outside of
literalism which of course they do then
then I don't think it's I don't think
we're blaspheming to say that that we
have to I don't think I don't think it's
a trivial statement and you just say
that we have to be stocker cheese
because the way that Socrates is
Socrates you know I trust you'll both
take this in in the intended meaning
even Socrates is not Socrates yes yes so
yeah in a way that's that's precisely
right we have to be Socrates in the way
that Socrates is and is not Socrates
precisely this isn't crazy says never
beyond himself I hope that's not I hope
that's not you reckon so that himself if
he said what's that you know I've given
you a Socrates more beautiful yeah yeah
that's right the historical Socrates
because he was much more concerned to
represent what Socrates lived for than
what Socrates was historically you know
again instead of pursuing this to the
historical certainty of Socrates Plato
was much more interested in getting us
to confront the truth of Socrates or the
SF arm of Socrates does it work
there we go Andrew the essence the form
and the truth of sanity's yes and we
have to end this I was also thinking
about the meaning of you know Carl Jung
talks about imitation of Christ is is
not imitating Christ's life but it is
becoming more truly not ourselves but
our I guess the again our divine double
like you keep using that if bringing
that that was it the my last question
and that keeps coming up at the end of
these conversations as well this notion
of the divine double which I talked
about with Zack as well and and the
divine double being our potential and
our plurality and it's enacted now I
mean it's simple it's symbolically
already active in how it calls us forth
from our current self yes
and yeah I think the I mean part of what
I want to work on with Chris's I think
there's a deep connection between wisdom
the sense of faith Socratic faith and
being in the correct kind of
connectedness and identity with your
sacred second self which which also is
more or less which is which is very
convergent with the idea of being in the
right relation to your whole self in the
Union sense of self right to find the
midpoint of personality that you in
talks about to be in relation with
yourself such that you're you're you
it's reciprocal and equilibrated spirit
and transfer or I might say translucent
for the distance distanced in just the
right way that you are you are you are
you are not susceptible to to two
pathologies of inflation and over
identification or God likeness but but
that you are that you are positioned
you're positioned you know in proportion
to your to your psychic potential
properly and I think that's very much
very much very if not I don't want to
make an argument from exact identity
here but I think I think the convergence
is pretty unmistakable yeah I would
agree with that
I would agree with that mmm-hmm I should
get going soon so but it's it is this
sound this feels like what we've also
come to a culmination point in the
conversation mm-hmm
yeah what do you think does anybody else
want to say anything or I don't want to
foreclose but I like I said I'm already
sort of half an hour past where I said I
would yeah well I wouldn't end this I I
would never end this it's such a great
pleasure for me and I appreciate it so
much but but there has to be an end
somewhere so well it's one of the only
things I like from Sartre you know he
said you never we talked about books he
said you never finished them you just
abandon them
and I don't think just abandon them
because we have other cars the car
station will continue in
well that's part of what we were talking
about towards the end in Austin yeah
it's what's moving forward and so
whatever it will become and I also there
was one point in their conversation
where I felt this is so important
I just wish like one person out there
could hear it there's just I don't even
remember what the point was but but
there's something really really
important in this conversation I mean I
mean there's a lot of things that are
really really important but even just
getting a little little piece of that
meaning could change everything I mean
does that make any sense am I being too
dramatic here no no no I think that's I
think that's that's that's that's
perfectly appropriate one thing you can
do to help that is as you've done before
and I've been slowly up I was gonna
upload our second conversation this
weekend but I thought that the
conversations with Jordan Hall were more
you know we're more appropriate given
their subject matter can I can send me
the files from this conversation I'll
upload it onto my channel and promoted
of course yeah yeah I'd love to talk to
you again
Christopher sometime and likewise thank
you anytime thank you thank you and
thank you for having just having the
having the wherewithal to actually bring
us together and to organize it and just
like I feel I feel like I mean I'm
indebted to the to the initiative that
youth that you've shown it all of this
and the delicacy and just the good taste
and good sense that you've shown in all
of this thank you you're so you're so
important to all of this Andrew and I'm
really that variable I'm grateful for
you and grateful now to have to know you
and I'm I'm grateful for all that you're
doing yes thank you thank you so thank
you so much that's that means a lot to
me that you that you would say that and
I think you guys are doing the deep
scholarship and and you know hopefully
I'm helping to communicate some of your
ideas and get it get them out there and
I think they will be meaningful to
people and that's my hope and wish I
wanted to also think
for the work that he's doing with
guy-guy cents doc reading through the
chapter and then trying to exemplify
idea logos by going through the Platonic
dialogues I think that's just an
invaluable resource and I'm like I'm
just very very grateful to be done so
thank you Chris for that well you're
you're another one supplies it lies at
the heart of all of my all of my
dialogic reelection so it says there's
no there's no none of this without you
John
you know that's true mm-hmm well I'm
looking forward to diving into that and
and I think I get my news from from you
guys you guys are like the news rather
than the other news that's going on this
is like the real news so thanks a lot in
and be well and take care and good
health to you and your family's in
YouTube and you be well and be safe and
John gets him all the ones you love yeah
thank you so much guys have a good one
okay you take care